<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Voip, | Lei Wu, Web Developer]]></title>
  <link href="http://wuleicanada.github.io/blog/categories/voip/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://wuleicanada.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-08T18:36:24+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://wuleicanada.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lei Wu]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Free Conference Call System]]></title>
    <link href="http://wuleicanada.github.io/blog/2015/12/08/building-a-free-conference-call-system/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-08T15:30:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://wuleicanada.github.io/blog/2015/12/08/building-a-free-conference-call-system</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I built a conference call system on my Windows 7 laptop, using Oracle VirtualBox, Asterisk and FreePBX.</p>

<p>I signed up a free account at CallCentric so that callers can dial in using iNum or SIP.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s more of a hobbyist project. Since I&rsquo;m familiar with all the pieces, one day I thought &ldquo;Why not put them together to make something interesting?&rdquo;</p>

<p>So here we go.</p>

<h2>Install VirtualBox</h2>

<p>Asterisk, the open source PBX system with built-in conference features, only lives on Linux. But I only have a Windows 7 laptop available for this project. Therefore VirtualBox.</p>

<p>After downloading it from <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/wiki/Downloads">https://www.virtualbox.org/wiki/Downloads</a> , installation is straightforward.</p>

<h2>Install AsteriskNow</h2>

<p>AsteriskNow is a combined distro of Centos, Asterisk and FreePBX. Get it from here and follow the instructions:
<a href="https://wiki.asterisk.org/wiki/display/AST/Installing+AsteriskNOW">https://wiki.asterisk.org/wiki/display/AST/Installing+AsteriskNOW</a></p>

<h2>Change VirtualBox network settings</h2>

<p>FreePBX is web based admin GUI for Asterisk. Since my VirtualBox guest system is only a terminal without GUI, I can&rsquo;t access any web pages from the VM.
I did try a text-based browser called <a href="http://lynx.browser.org/">Lynx</a> but unfortunately the FreePBX admin interface requires JavaScript, which Lynx
doesn&rsquo;t support.</p>

<p>Next, I tried to access the Admin interface <code>http://10.0.2.15</code> from my Windows host, but it was unreachable.</p>

<p>Then I realized 10.0.2.15 was just a VirtualBox IP. The solution is quite simple, just change the network adapter
from &ldquo;NAT&rdquo; to &ldquo;Bridged Adapter&rdquo;. This can be done from &ldquo;Machine&rdquo; -> &ldquo;Settings&rdquo; -> &ldquo;Network&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Now my guest system has a real IP, accessible from my Windows hosts.</p>

<h2>Create a Conference in FreePBX</h2>

<p>Go to FreePBX admin GUI at <code>http://IP_OF_YOUR_ASTERISK</code>, then click &ldquo;Applications&rdquo; -> &ldquo;Conferences&rdquo; to add a new conference.</p>

<h2>Sign up a CallCentric free account</h2>

<p>DID numbers are not free at CallCentric, but <a href="http://www.inum.net">iNum</a> numbers are. Callers can reach my conference room by calling the iNum number.</p>

<p>There are three ways to reach an iNum number:</p>

<ul>
<li>If your phone provider supports it (such as CallCentric, voip.ms, etc.), you can dial it like <code>+883 510 xxxxxxxxx</code>. In the United States and Canada, + means 011.</li>
<li>Use one of the <a href="http://www.inum.net/what-is-inum-2/local-access-numbers/">local dial in numbers</a></li>
<li>Use SIP URI <code>8835100xxxxxxxx@sip.inum.net</code></li>
</ul>


<p>Alternatively, because CallCentric support SIP calls, it&rsquo;s also possible to call your CallCentric number 1777xxxxxxx using one of the following methods:</p>

<ul>
<li>SIP peering if your provider supports it, <code>**275 *462 1777xxxxxxx</code></li>
<li><a href="http://sipbroker.com/">SipBroker</a> (code *462)</li>
<li>SIP URI <code>1777xxxxxxx@in.callcentric.com</code></li>
</ul>


<h2>Set up CallCentric in FreePBX</h2>

<p>Follow the <a href="http://www.callcentric.com/support/device/freepbx">official instructions from CallCentric</a> to set it up in FreePBX.</p>

<p>In my case, I only need to configure trunk (Step 1) and inbound route. I don&rsquo;t really care about outbound route or extension.</p>

<p>My Asterisk version is 13, so I used the configuration for the latest Asterisk in the PEER Details section.</p>

<p>I also route all incoming calls to the Conference I created earlier.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>My conference room is up and running! And completely free of charge! Well&hellip; if three hours of my time doesn&rsquo;t count :-)</p>

<p>Asterisk is very powerful, enough for serious business usage. I&rsquo;m just using a fraction of it and already amazed by its versatility.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
